Guide to the Paulette Goddard Papers MSS.197
Fales Library and Special Collections
Paulette Goddard Papers
1919-1987
Fales Library and Special Collections
Goddard, Paulette, 1911-1990
MSS.197
9 Linear Feet in 7 manuscript boxes, 2 oversize folders, and 25 flat boxes.
Paulette Goddard was an actress and socialite, most famous for her roles in Modern Times and The Great Dictator, which she starred in with her then husband Charlie Chaplin. In addition to her marriage to Charlie Chaplin, she also was married to actor Burgess Meredith and novelist Erich Maria Remarque. The Paulette Goddard Papers date from 1919 to 1987 and mostly contain scrapbooks of clippings of Goddard in the press, focusing on films she was in, her relationships, events she attended, and other publicity as a movie star. The collection also contains some personal material, including family photographs, correspondence with her mother and her husband Remarque, and awards.
Biographical Note
Paulette Goddard was an actress and socialite, most famous for her roles in Modern Times and The Great Dictator, which she starred in with her then husband Charlie Chaplin. Goddard was a member of the Ziegfield Follies and starred in at least 65 films, mainly for Paramount Pictures throughout the 1940s and 1950s. In addition to her marriage to Charlie Chaplin, she also was married to actor Burgess Meredith and Erich Maria Remarque, a German novelist most known for All Quiet on the Western Front. After her film career, she remained famous as a socialite and through her personal wealth. Goddard gave New York University a substantial gift named in honor of Remarque. She died on April 23, 1990. Goddard Hall, a freshman dorm, is named for her.
Scope and Contents
The Paulette Goddard Papers date from 1919 to 1987 and mostly contain scrapbooks of clippings of Goddard in the press, focusing on films she was in, her relationships, events she attended, and other publicity as a movie star during the peak of her career in the 1930s through the 1950s. Other professional materials include bound screenplays, headshots, film stills, and posters. The collection also contains some personal material, including family photographs, correspondence with her mother and her husband Erich Maria Remarque, and awards.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into two series:
Series I: Personal
Series II: Professional
Each series is arranged alphabetically by folder title.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Related Materials
Erich Maria Remarque Papers (MSS 095)
Custodial History
The majority of Paulette Goddard's estate was bequeathed to New York Unversity in 1986. It is unknown when the collection came to Fales but likely after her death in 1990.
Separated Materials
29 engraved books to Goddard, Charlie Chaplin, and Burgess Meredith were separated to the Fales Library Collection and will be cataloged individually:
Aldous Huxley: A Biography; Bedford, Sybille
Algeria From Within; Bodley, R. V. C.
Adventures in Genius; Durant, Will
Two copies of Transition: A Sentimental Story of One Mind and One Era; Durant, Will
Art and the Life of Action; Eastman, Max
Jinx: The Story of Jinx Falkenburg; Falkenburg, Jinx
The Rubáiyát of Omar Khayyám; Fitzgerald, Edward and Whinfield, E. H.
Beau James: The Life and Times of Jimmy Walker; Fowler, Gene
Gina; Glay, George Albert
A Guide for the Bedevilled; Hecht, Ben
Four Plays; Hellman, Lillian
The Gap of Brightness; Higgins, F. R.
Neurosis and Human Growth: The Struggle Toward Self-Realization; Horney, Karen
The Magic Curtain; Lagner, Lawrence
The Importance of Wearing Clothes; Langer, Lawrence
A Mouse is Born; Loos, Anita
Return to the Vineyard; Loos, Mary and Duranty, Walter
Im Westen nichts Neues; Maria Remarque, Erich
The Selected Poetry of Robinson Jeffers
Brave Men; Pyle, Ernie
World's End; Sinclair, Upton
Between Two Worlds; Sinclair, Upton
All Things Considered; Sterne Carrington, Elaine
The Male Animal; Thurber James and Nugent, Elliott
Out of the Night; Valtin, Jan
Things To Come; Wells, H. G.
While Rome Burns; Woollcott, Alexander
Clippings (information artifacts); Motion picture actors and actresses.; Film stills.; Screenplays; Remarque, Erich Maria, 1898-1970; Chaplin, Charlie, 1889-1977; Meredith, Burgess, 1907-1997
- Series I: Personal, 1919-1969; 1 Linear Feet in 1 manuscript box and 3 flat boxes.
  Scope and Contents
  Series I contains correspondence with Goddard's mother, Alta, her third husband Erich Maria Remarque, and other friends and colleagues, including Louella Parsons, Carmel Snow, Diego Rivera, Walter Plunkett, Helga Löwenstein, and Catherine Hunter, secretary of Chaplin Studios. There is also some correspondence from fans and veterans who saw her shows touring with the United Service Organizations.
  The series also includes personal photographs of her travel and family, art, awards, and other personal materials related to her and Remarque's publishing activities. Goddard's portrait was drawn by multiple different artists and included in the collection. There is also some material related to her other husbands, including photographs from her wedding to Burgess Meredith and pictures of her with Charlie Chaplin.
  Arrangement
  Arranged alphabetically by format.
  - Award Certificates, 1940s (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Book Plate, undated (Box 16)
  - Correspondence, 1935-1949 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1951-1963 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1952-1960 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1959-1961 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence--Alta Goddard, 1952-1964 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Drawing, undated (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Drawing of Goddard, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Drawings of Goddard, 1940-1961 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Fine Art Reprints--Lillian MacKendrick, Diego Rivera, circa 1950s (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Jewelry Box, undated (Box 16)
  - Photo Album, 1919-1929 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Photographs--Burgess Meredith, 1940s (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Photographs--Charlie Chaplin, circa 1936-1942 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Photographs--Mexico, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Photographs--Mexico Trip, undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Photographs--Remarque, 1950s-1960s (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Photographs--Wedding to Burgess Meredith, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Receipts, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Ron Rico Membership Certificate, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Telegrams, 1957-1962 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - The Black Obelisk Poster, 1956 (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - United Jewish Welfare Fund Award, undated (Box 9, Folder 2)
- Series II: Professional, 1926-1987; 8 Linear Feet 6 manuscript boxes, 2 oversize folders and 22 flat boxes.
  The majority of Series II contains scrapbooks of clippings that mention Paulette Goddard in the press, dating from the 1930s-1950s. The clippings cover her time as a her time as a Ziegfeld Follies girl, her relationship with Charlie Chaplin, the making of Modern Times, her work with the United Service Organizations (USO), and publicity for other films in the American and foreign press. The series also includes posters and screenplays from movies Goddard starred in, as well as film stills. Other photographic material include headshots of Goddard, as well as other actors and actresses, some of which are signed.
  Arranged alphabetically by format then chronologically.
  - Autographed Photographs, undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Autographed Photographs, undated (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Clippings, 1926-1932 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Clippings, circa 1933-1936 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Clippings, circa 1933-1936 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Clippings, 1949 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Clippings Scrapbook, 1934-1935 (Box 17)
  - Clippings Scrapbook, 1935 (Box 16)
  - Clippings Scrapbook, 1935-1936 (Box 21)
  - Clippings Scrapbook, 1936 (Box 14)
  - Clippings Scrapbook, 1936-1937 (Box 23)
  - Clippings Scrapbook, 1936-1937 (Box 24)
  - Clippings Scrapbook, 1937-1938 (Box 23)
  - Clippings Scrapbook, 1938-1939 (Box 12)
  - Clippings Scrapbook, 1939 (Box 13)
  - Clippings Scrapbook, 1939-1940 (Box 13)
  - Clippings Scrapbook, 1940 (Box 12)
  - Clippings Scrapbook, 1940 (Box 15)
  - Clippings Scrapbook, 1941 (Box 14)
  - Clippings Scrapbook, 1941-1942 (Box 11)
  - Clippings Scrapbook, 1941-1944 (Box 11)
  - Clippings Scrapbook, 1943-1945 (Box 15)
  - Clippings Scrapbook, 1943-1945 (Box 32)
  - Clippings Scrapbook, 1945-1946 (Box 31)
  - Clippings Scrapbook, 1947 (Box 25)
  - Clippings Scrapbook, 1947 (Box 26)
  - Clippings Scrapbook, 1949 (Box 28)
  - Clippings Scrapbook, 1950-1952 (Box 29)
  - Clippings Scrapbook, 1952-1953 (Box 27)
  - Clippings Scrapbook, 1953-1956 (Box 18)
  - Clippings Scrapbook, 1956-1960 (Box 19)
  - Clippings Scrapbook, 1960-1981 (Box 20)
  - Clippings Scrapbook, 1972-1983 (Box 30)
  - Clippings Scrapbook--Modern Times, 1935 (Box 22)
  - Clippings Scrapbook--Modern Times, 1935-1936 (Box 16)
  - Clippings Scrapbook--Modern Times, 1936 (Box 21)
  - Clippings Scrapbook--Modern Times, 1936 (Box 22)
  - Clippings Scrapbook--Modern Times, 1936 (Box 24)
  - Diary of a Chambermaid Press, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Fan-made Scrapbook, 1940s (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Filmography and Biography, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Headshots, 1930s-1940s (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Headshots, circa 1930s-1950s (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Headshots, 1941-1947 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Licensing Agreement for the Last Station to Otto Preminger, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Life Magazine, 1945 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Look Magazine, 1940-1956 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Movie Show, 1948 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Negatives, 1940s (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Paulette Goddard Film Festival, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Paulette Goddard International Club Publication, 1937-1939 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Photographs, 1930s (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Photographs, 1940s (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Photographs, 1950s (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Photographs, circa 1930s-1970s (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Photographs--A Miracle Can Happen, 1948 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Photographs--An Ideal Husband, 1947 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Photographs--Bride of Vengeance, 1949 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Photographs--CNAC, 1942-1944 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Photographs--Diary of a Chambermaid, 1946 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Photographs--Duffy's Tavern, 1945 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Photographs--Goddard with Blonde Hair, 1930s (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Photographs--Hazard, 1948 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Photographs--Kitty, 1945 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Photographs--Marlene Dietrich, 1930s (Box 8, Folder 1-3, Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Photographs--Modern Times, 1936 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Photographs--Nothing But the Truth, 1941 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Photographs--Odd Man Out, 1947 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Photographs--Paramount Pictures, 1940-1948 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Photographs--Pot o' Gold, 1941 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Photographs--Ray Milland, 1942 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Photographs--Reap the Wild Wind, 1942 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Photographs--Second Chorus, 1940 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Photographs--Suddenly It's Spring, 1947 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Photographs--The Ghost Breakers, 1940 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Photographs--The Great Dictator, 1940 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Photographs--The Women, 1939 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Photographs--Unconquered, 1947 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Photographs--USO, 1940s (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Photographs--Visit to the Ministry of Food, 1946 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Portraits, 1920s-1940s (Box 8, Folder 8-9)
  - Portraits, 1940s (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Posters--Kitty, The Women, and North West Mountain Police, 1939-1945 (Folder 7 Right)
  - Posters--Modern Times, Second Chorus, Diary of a Chambermaid, and The Great Dictator, 1936-1946 (Folder 1)
  - Posters--On Our Merry Way and An Ideal Husband, 1947-1948 (Folder 9)
  - Publicity, 1936-1987 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Screen Guild Theatre Radio Signature Book, 1942-1945 (Box 10)
  - Screenplay--A Miracle Can Happen, 1946 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Screenplay--An Ideal Husband, 1947 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Screenplay--Anna Lucasta, 1949 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Screenplay--Bride of Vengeance, 1948 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Screenplay--Charge of the Lancers, 1952 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Screenplay--Harness Bull, 1952 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Screenplay--Hazard, 1947 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Screenplay--Kitty, 1944 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Screenplay--Paris Model, 1953 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Screenplay--Sins of Jezebel, 1953 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Screenplay--Suddenly It's Spring, 1946 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Screenplay--The Galileans, 1957 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Screenplay--Unconquered, 1946 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Script--Time and Again, 1956 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - US Treasury Department Citation, 1942 (Box 8, Folder 5)